Louis E. Phaneuf Papers MS202
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Louis E. Phaneuf Papers
1917 -- 1953
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Phaneuf, Louis Eusebe
MS202
0.4 Linear Feet 1 box
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Biographical information; Publications; and Awards and Certificates.
Custodial History
The bulk of these materials were found in the Tufts University School of Medicine in 2012.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains biographical information related to Dr. Louis E. Phaneuf, as well as awards and certificates awarded to him, and bound volumes of his publications.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Louis Eusebe Phaneuf was born in St. Hilaire, Quebec, Canada on February 27, 1884.
In September, 1909, Phaneuf entered the Tufts College of Medicine. He already held a Doctor of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Chemistry from the Massachusetts College of Pharmacy at the time. He graduated from Tufts in 1913 and started his first internship in the Department of Gynecology at the Carney Hospital. Following further periods of training at the Lying-in Hospital in New York and the Free Hospital in Brookline, Massachusetts, he entered practice. He also returned to Tufts to start teaching. He was an Assistant Professor from 1915 to 1920, an Associate Professor from 1920 to 1927, and attained the rank of Full Professor in the Department of Gynecology in 1927. In addition to his medical practice and teaching responsibilities, Phaneuf served as a First Lieutenant in World War I.
A leader in the fields of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Phaneuf received numerous accolades throughout his career. In 1933, the Trustees of Tufts College bestowed him with a Honorary Degree, and in 1938, Phaneuf was made an officer of the Order of the Crown by King Leopold of Belgium.
Phaneuf died September 20, 1953. He was survived by his wife Florence who passed away in 1973. They had no children.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Alumni collections; Faculty papers; University history; Tufts University -- History
- Biographical information, 1919 -- 1953; MS202.001; 0.4 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical information about Phaneuf from his University vertical file. Much of it dates from the time of his death in 1953.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Phaneuf, Louis E. (1884-1953) vertical files, 1919 -- 1953; MS202.001.001.00001 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
- Publications, 1917 -- 1933; MS202.002; 0.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains bound volumes of publications written by Dr. Louis E. Phaneuf.
  - Gynecological and Obstetrical Papers Book I, 1917 -- 1929; MS202.002.001.00002 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
    monographs
  - Gynecological and Obstetrical Papers Book II, 1924 -- 1933; MS202.002.001.00003 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
- Awards and certificates, 1920 -- 1953; MS202.003; 0.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains awards and certificates from professional organizations and Tufts College. There is also one frame of evidential value.
  - Fellow of the American College of Surgeons, 1920; MS202.003.001.00004 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Fellow of the American College of Surgeons frame, 1920; MS202.003.001.00005 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - American Association of Obstetricians, Gynecologists and Abdominal Surgeons Fellowship, 1923; MS202.003.001.00006 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Societe Belge de Gynecologie et d'Obstetrique member correspondant, 1925; MS202.003.001.00007 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Societe Belge de Gynecologie et d'Obstetrique member Honoraire, 1926; MS202.003.001.00008 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Letter from the Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology in Paris, 1926; MS202.003.001.00009 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
    In French.
  - New England Obstetrical and Gynecological Society membership, 1929; MS202.003.001.00010 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - American Board of Obstetrics and Gynecology certificate, 1930; MS202.003.001.00011 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Societe Internationale de Chirurgie membership nomination, 1932; MS202.003.001.00012 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Los Angeles Obstetrical and Gynecological Society Honorary membership, 1933 -- 1953; MS202.003.001.00013 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Smithsonian Institution Patron certificate, 1933 -- 1953; MS202.003.001.00014 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Trustees and Officers of Tufts College Certificate of Appreciation, 1933 -- 1953; MS202.003.001.00015 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Tufts College Distinguished Service Key, 1933 -- 1953; MS202.003.001.00016 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - New England Obstetrical and Gynecological Society president, 1935 -- 1936; MS202.003.001.00017 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Societatae de Gynecologie din Bucuresti honorary member, 1936; MS202.003.001.00018 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Alpha Omega Alpha membership, 1940; MS202.003.001.00019 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Fellow of the Academy International of Medicine, 1944; MS202.003.001.00020 (Box MS202 Shared 1)
  - Society of the Sigma Xi diploma, 1945; MS202.003.001.00021 (Box MS202 Shared 1)